麦努森先生 请说出你的全名 便于案件记录
Mr Magnussen, please state your full name for the record.
查尔斯·奥古斯都·麦努森
Charles Augustus Magnussen.
麦努森先生
Mr Magnussen,
你认为你对首相的影响力如何?
how would you describe your influence over the Prime Minister?
英国首相?
The British Prime Minister?
任何你认识的英国首相
Any of the British Prime Ministers you have known.
我对任何首相都没有影响力
I never had the slightest influence over any of them.
我为什么能影响首相?
Why would I?
我注意到 今年你在唐宁街参与了七次会谈
I notice you've had seven meetings at Downing Street this year.
为什么?
Why?
因为我受到了邀请
Because I was invited.
你能否回忆起会谈的内容?
Can you recall the subjects under discussion?
我认为内容都很正常
Not without being more indiscreet than I believe is appropriate.
你觉得 作为一位报社社长
Do you think it right that a newspaper proprietor,
一个个人 事实上还是一位外籍人士
a private individual, and in fact a foreign national,
与我们的首相进行如此经常性会晤是否正常?
should have such regular access to our Prime Minister?
我觉得 作为个人 接受邀请
I don't think it's wrong that a private individual should
并没什么错
accept an invitation.
不过 我真诚地道歉 我是一个外国人
However, you have my sincere apologies for being foreign.
我不是这个意思 这怎么可能...
That's not what I meant. That is not in any way...
麦努森先生 你是否记得在一些情况下
Mr Magnussen, can you recall an occasion
您的意见以任何形式影响了政府政策?
when your remarks could have influenced a government policy?
或首相的思路呢?
Or the Prime Minister's thinking in any way?
没有这样的情况
No.
你确定吗?
Are you sure?
(伊丽莎白·斯莫尔伍德女士)
(弱点: 丈夫)
我的记忆力很好
I have an excellent memory.
您的车就停在外面... 明天见
Your car is waiting outside... See you tomorrow.
我能坐那吗?
May I join you?
我认为这并不合适
I don't think it's appropriate.
- 确实不合适  - 麦努森先生 除了在质询会上 我们不能有
- It isn't.  - Mr Magnussen, outside the inquiry, we can have no contact,
任何接触或交流
no communication at all.
请不要这样
Please don't do that.
1982年 你丈夫与海伦·凯瑟琳·得利斯科尔通信
In 1982, your husband corresponded with Helen Catherine Driscoll.
那是我认识他之前
That was before I knew him.
那些信可真是生动 充满爱意...
The letters were lively, loving...
有些还很露骨
some would say explicit.
这些信目前在我手里
And currently in my possession.
能不能把你的手拿开?
Will you please move your hand?
"亲爱的 我渴望抚摸你的... 胴体"
"I long, my darling, to know the touch of your... body."
我知道信里有这句话
I know what was in the letters.
她才15岁
She was 15.
她看上去很成熟
She looked older.
哦 她看上去也很诱人 我们还有照片为证
Oh, she looked delicious. We have photographs too.
她寄给他的照片
The ones she sent him.
真美味啊
Yum-yum.
他那时不知道她的年龄
He was unaware of her age.
在通信之前 他只见过她一次
He met her only once before the letters began.
当他发现真相后 马上就停止了通信
When he discovered the truth, he stopped immediately.
事实就是这样
Those are the facts.
事实是历史书里才有的东西 我是做新闻的
Facts are for history books. I work in news.
你的手在出汗
Your hand is sweating.
我一直在出汗 不好意思 我有一个条件
Always, I'm afraid. I have a condition.
真恶心
It's disgusting.
我已经习惯了
I'm used to it.
整个世界都在我的股掌之中
The whole world is wet to my touch.
我要叫保安把你赶走
I will call someone, I will have you removed.
那是什么味道?
What is that?
月色?
Claire de la Lune?
你用有点年轻 不是吗?
A bit young for you, isn't it?
你现在想打我? 还有力气吗?
You want to hit me now? Could you, still?
现在你只是个小老女人罢了
Little old lady now.
或许你该收拾收拾准备叫人吧
Perhaps you should settle for calling someone.
叫人啊
Well, go on.
怎么不叫了?
No?
因为现在有结果了
Because now there are consequences.
我手里有那些信 因此你就在我手里
I have the letters and therefore I have you.
这是敲诈
This is blackmail.
这显然不是敲诈
Of course it isn't blackmail.
这是...
This is...
所有权
ownership.
你并没有拥有我
You do not own me.
月色
Claire de la Lune.
它尝起来可没有闻起来好 是吧?
It never tastes like it smells, does it?
斯莫尔伍德女士的消费记在我账上 别忘了
Lady Smallwood's bill is on me. See to it.
好的 麦努森先生
Yes, Mr Magnussen.
天啊! 哦!
Oh, God! Oh!
您没事吧 夫人?
You all right, ma'am?
没事
Fine, yes.
麦努森!
Magnussen!
没人反对他
No one stands up to him.
没人敢对付他 甚至都没人试着对付他
No one dares, no one even tries.
在英国没有一个人能够阻止
There isn't a man or woman in England capable of stopping
那个恶心的东西...
that disgusting creature...
夫人?
Ma'am?
掉头 我们回市区 掉头
Turn the car around. We're going back into town. Turn around.
我们去哪里 夫人?
Where are we going, ma'am?
贝克街
Baker Street.
《神探夏洛克》
你见过很多伤员? 死状惨烈?
You've seen a lot of injuries, then? Violent deaths?
够看一辈子的了 还想看更多吗?
Enough for a lifetime. Want to see some more?
天啊 想
Oh, God, yes.
游戏开始了
The game is on.
《最后的誓言》
我知道现在很早 真的很抱歉
I know it's early. Really, I'm sorry.
- 是凯特吗?  - 对 是凯特
- Is that Kate?  - Yeah, it's Kate.
不请她进来?
Invite her in?
呃 不好意思 请进 凯特
Er, sorry, yes, do you want to come in, Kate?
嘿!
Hey!
我知道这很难
It's hard.
- 给  - 是艾萨克
- There you go.  - It's Isaac.
- 哦 你丈夫?  - 是儿子
- Oh, your husband?  - Son.
儿子 对
Son, yeah.
他又不见了 昨晚都没回家
He's gone missing again. Didn't come home last night.
他经常这样
The usual.
他吸毒 是吗?
He's the drugs one, yeah?
没错 说得真委婉 约翰
Er, yeah, nicely put, John.
但你是不是想找夏洛克·福尔摩斯? 我好久没见他了
But is it Sherlock Holmes you want? Because I've not seen him in ages.
- 大概一个月  - 谁是夏洛克·福尔摩斯?
- About a month.  - Who is Sherlock Holmes?
看到了吧 还是有人不知道的
See, that does happen.
有个地方他们总去 他和他的朋友
There's a place they all go to, him and his friends.
他们做他们想做的任何事
They all do whatever they do.
嗨一下 随便你怎么叫
Shoot up, whatever you call it.
- 他在哪?  - 那是座房子 垃圾场 实际上快塌了
- Where is he?  - It's a house, it's a dump. It's practically falling down.
不是 我是说地址? 具体的地址?
No, the address? Where, exactly?
- 你玩真的?  - 不然呢?
- Seriously?  - Why not?
她不会去报警 总得有人去找她儿子
She's not going to the police, someone's got to get him.
- 为什么是你?  - 要乐于助人
- Why you?  - I'm being neighbourly.
- 从什么时候开始的?  - 从现在开始 从这分钟开始
- Since when?  - Ha, since now. Since this exact minute.
- 你为什么这么...?  - 什么?
- Why are you being so...?  - What?
我不知道 你怎么回事?
I don't know, what's the matter with you?
我没什么事
There is nothing the matter with me.
- 设想我刚才没吼你  - 我在努力中
- Imagine I said that without shouting.  - I'm trying.
不行 你不能去 你怀孕了
No, you can't come, you're pregnant.
你才不能去 你要做爸爸了!
You can't go, I'm pregnant!
那是什么?!
What is that?!
- 是轮胎撬杆  - 为什么带这个?
- It's a tyre lever.  - Why?
因为那里有一群瘾君子 搞不好可能需要修轮胎
Cos there were loads of smackheads in there and one of them might need help with a tyre.
如果有麻烦 你直接走 不用担心我
If there's any trouble, just go, I'll be fine.
约翰 约翰 约翰 约翰...
John, John, John, John...
这样还是有点小性感哦
It is a tiny bit sexy.
我知道
Yeah, I know.
有人吗?
Hello?
(私人财产 禁止入内)
- 你想怎样?  - 借过一下
- What do you want?  - Excuse me.
不行 你不能进来!
Oh, no, you can't come in here!
我在找一个朋友 一个特定的... 朋友
I'm looking for a friend. A very specific... friend.
我不是随便逛逛
I'm not just browsing.
你得出去 这里不允许别人进来
You've got to go. No one's allowed here.
艾萨克·惠特尼 你见过他吗?
Isaac Whitney, you seen him?
我在问你 你有没有见过艾萨克·惠特尼
I'm asking you if you've seen Isaac Whitney
现在你却拿出一把刀来
and now you're showing me a knife.
这是线索? 你在演哑剧吗?
Is it a clue? Are you doing a mime?
滚 否则我就一刀切了你
Go. Or I'll cut you.
哦 那里太远了 我来帮帮你吧
Oh, not from there. Let me help.
现在 集中注意力 艾萨克·惠特尼?
Now, concentrate. Isaac Whitney?
好的 你自找的
OK, you asked for it.
好了 现在你的注意力集中了吗?
Right. Are you concentrating yet?
你打断了我的胳膊!
You broke my arm!
没有 我只是扭了一下
No, I sprained it.
感觉软绵绵的 扭伤的感觉是软绵绵的吗?
It feels squishy. Is it supposed to feel squishy?
- 你来摸一下!  - 没错 就是扭伤
- Feel that!  - Yeah, it's a sprain.
我是个医生 我知道怎么扭伤人
I'm a doctor, I know how to sprain people.
现在回答我 艾萨克·惠特尼在哪里?
Now where is Isaac Whitney?
我不知道! 可能在楼上
I don't know! Maybe upstairs.
这不就结了 不是很简单吗?
There you go. Wasn't that easy?
不 很疼啊
No, it was really sore.
疯子 你就是个疯子!
Mental, you are!
不是 只是见多了高端罪犯而已
No, just used to a better class of criminal.
艾萨克? 艾萨克·惠特尼?
Isaac? Isaac Whitney?
艾萨克?
Isaac?
嘿 兄弟 给我坐直了 坐直
Hello, mate. Sit up for me, sit up.
- 华生医生?  - 没错
- Dr Watson?  - Yep.
我在哪里?
Where am I?
和一堆垃圾窝在粪堆里 看着我
Arse-end of the universe with the scum of the earth. Look at me.
你是来找我的?
Have you come for me?
你觉得我认识这里很多人吗?
Do you think I know a lot of people here?
嘿 还好吗?
Hey, all right?
你好 约翰 没想到在这里见到你
Oh, hello, John. Didn't expect to see you here.
你也来找我?
Come for me too?
- 你好 艾萨克  - 华生太太 我能不能上车?
- Hello, Isaac.  - Mrs Watson, can I, can I get in, please?
- 当然可以 上车吧 约翰在哪里?  - 他们在吵架
- Yes, of course, get in. Where's John?  - They're having a fight.
和谁?!
Who is?!
看在上帝的份上 约翰 我在查案!
For God sakes, John, I'm on a case!
一个月 这个月你就这么过的
A month. That's all it took.
只有一晚! 我在工作
One! I'm working.
"夏洛克·福尔摩斯在吸毒窝点" 这个标题如何?!
"Sherlock Holmes in a drug den." How's that going to look?!
- 我是卧底  - 不 你不是!
- I'm undercover.  - No, you're not!
好吧 现在我不是了!
Well, I'm not now!
上车 你们两个 快!
In, both of you, quickly!
行行好 能让我上车吗? 我想我胳膊断了
Please, can I come? I think I've got a broken arm.
- 不行 走开  - 算了 让他上车吧
- No, go away.  - No, let him.
- 为什么?  - 上来吧 只是扭伤而已
- Why?  - Yeah, just get in. It's a sprain.
还有人吗? 我是说 我们要把所有人都接回家 是吗?
Anyone else? I mean, are we taking everybody home, are we?
你还好吗 夏札?
All right, Shezza?
- 夏札?  - 我那时候在卧底!
- Shezza?  - I was undercover!
说真的 也别用夏札吧?
Seriously, Shezza, though?
- 我们先不回家 我们去巴特医院 我给茉莉打电话  - 为什么?
- We're not going home, we're going to Bart's. I'm calling Molly.  - Why?
因为夏洛克·福尔摩斯要做尿检
Because Sherlock Holmes needs to pee in a jar.
好了? 他没吸吧?
Well? Is he clean?
没有
Clean.
你怎么敢糟蹋上天赐予你的身体!
How dare you throw away the beautiful gifts you were born with!
你怎么敢辜负朋友对你的关爱!
And how dare you betray the love of your friends!
你要道歉
Say you're sorry.
抱歉你的婚约没了 虽然我很庆幸你手上没带戒指
Sorry your engagement's over. Though I'm fairly grateful for the lack of a ring.
别吸了 别再吸了!
Stop it. Just stop it!
如果你毒瘾快要犯了
If you were anywhere near this kind of thing again,
你可以打电话 可以和我说
you could have called, you could have talked to me.
放心 别激动 都是为了查案
Please, do relax. This is all for a case.
什么样的案子需要你这样?
What kind of case would need you doing this?
我或许也要问问你 为什么你开始骑自行车上班了?
I might as well ask you why you've started cycling to work?
不 我们不玩这个游戏
No, we're not playing this game.
就在最近 而且你还下定了决心
Quite recently, I'd say, you're very determined about it.
- 我没兴趣  - 我有兴趣 疼!
- Not interested.  - I am. Ow!
不好意思 你刚才动了一下 不过只是扭伤
Oh, sorry, you moved, but it is just a sprain.
- 没错 有人打了我  - 啊?
- Yeah, somebody hit me.  - Huh?
对 有个人
Yeah, just some guy.
是啊 可能只是一个瘾君子需要修理修理
Yeah, it was probably just an addict in need of a fix.
对 我想从某个方面来说是的
Yes, I think in a way it was.
- 是他的衬衫吗?  - 你说什么?
- Is it his shirt?  - I'm sorry?
是衬衫的褶皱 是吗?
Well, it's the creases, isn't it?
前面有两条折痕
The two creases down the front.
折痕是新的 但衣服不是
It's been recently folded, but it's not new.
你今天早上一定是很匆忙地穿的衣服
You must have dressed in a hurry this morning.
所以你所有的衬衫都是那样叠着的
So all your shirts must be kept like that.
但是为什么呢?
But why?
也许是因为你每天骑车去上班 到了之后
Maybe cos you cycle to work every morning, shower
会冲个澡 再换上你带的衣服
when you get there and then dress in the clothes you brought with you.
你是把你的衬衫叠好了准备带走的
You keep your shirts folded, ready to pack.
不错啊
Not bad.
我进一步推断...
And I further deduce...
你是最近才开始骑车的 因为你的腿好像还有点擦伤
you've only started recently because you've got a bit of chafing.
这倒不是 他一向那样走路
No, he's always walked like that.
再说一遍 你叫什么来着?
Remind me, what's your name again?
- 他们叫我威格  - 不对
- They call me the Wig.  - No, they don't.
好吧 他们... 他们叫我维吉
Well, they... they call me Wiggy.
也不是
Nope.
比尔 比尔·维金斯
Bill. Bill Wiggins.
观察力不错嘛 比利
Nice observational skills, Billy.
终于好了!
Ah, finally!
- 终于什么?  - 是好消息?
- Finally what?  - Good news?
哦 这可是天大的好消息
Oh, excellent news, the best.
我重犯毒瘾的事可能要上报纸了
There's every chance that my drug habit might hit the newspapers.
游戏开始了 容我... 失陪一下
The game is on. Excuse me... for a second.
你听说过查尔斯·奥古斯都·麦努森吧?
You've heard of Charles Augustus Magnussen, of course?
知道 他有几家报社 但我不读那些报纸
Yeah. Owns some newspapers. Ones I don't read.
等下 其他人都哪去了?
Hang on, weren't there other people?
玛丽送那两个孩子回家 我送你 我们商量好的
Mary's taking the boys home, I'm taking you, we did discuss it.
人们在说话 而我又没有参与其中 我一定是把谈话过滤掉了
People were talking, none of them were me, I must have filtered.
- 我发现了  - 我总是过滤掉一堆没用的废话
- I noticed.  - I have to filter out a lot of witless babble.
我已经把哈德森太太调成半永久性静音了
I've got Mrs Hudson on semi-permanent mute.
我哥哥在这干嘛?
What is my brother doing here?
所以又得我付钱了 是吧?
So I'll just pay, then, shall I?
他摆正了门环
He's straightened the knocker.
他总在纠正我 这是强迫症 他自己都不知道自己在干什么
He always corrects it, it's OCD, doesn't even know he's doing it.
你为什么要这样?
Why do you do that?
- 怎样?  - 没事
- Do what?  - Nothing
好啊 夏洛克 老毛病又犯了?
Well then, Sherlock, back on the sauce?
- 你来这里干什么?  - 我给他打的电话
- What are you doing here?  - I phoned him.
旧病复发的警报 简直和鲁迪叔叔一样
The siren call of old habits. How very like Uncle Rudy.
- 不过从很多方面来看 变装倒可能是一条适合你的路  - 你给他打电话
- Though in many ways, cross-dressing would have been a wiser path for you.  - You phoned him.
- 我当然给他打电话了  - 他当然找我了
- Of course I bloody phoned him.  - Of course he bloody did.
长话短说吧 我们应该去哪找?
Now save me a little time, where should we be looking?
- 你们?  - 福尔摩斯先生?
- We?  - Mr Holmes?
天啊!
For God's sake!
- 安德森?!  - 对不起 夏洛克 这也是为你好
- Anderson?!  - Sorry, Sherlock, it's for your own good.
这就是他? 你描述的比他真人要高点
Oh, that's him, isn't it? You said he'd be taller.
这是你粉丝团的两位成员 要礼貌点
Some members of your little fan club. Do be polite.
他们绝对值得信任 而且甚至还愿意来调查
They're entirely trustworthy and even willing to search
这个你称之为公寓的有毒垃圾场
through the toxic waste dump that you are pleased to call a flat.
你是名人了 夏洛克
You're a celebrity these days, Sherlock.
你不能染上毒瘾
You can't afford a drug habit.
- 我没有染上毒瘾  - 嘿 我的椅子呢?
- I do not have a drug habit.  - Hey, what happened to my chair?
它挡住我看厨房的视线了
It was blocking my view to the kitchen.
好吧 被想念的感觉真不错!
Well, it's good to be missed!
- 你走了之后 我看到了一些新的机遇  - 不 你看到了厨房而已
- You were gone, I saw an opportunity.  - No, you saw the kitchen.
- 到目前为止 你发现了什么?  - 显然什么都没发现
- What have you found so far?  - Clearly, nothing.
没什么可发现的!
There's nothing to find!
你卧室的门是关着的 而你又整夜未归
Your bedroom door is shut. You haven't been home all night.
所以 为什么一个妈妈不提醒就从不知道关门的人
So, why would a man who has never knowingly closed a door without
现在突然要关门了呢?
the direct orders of his mother bother to do so on this occasion?
停下 别开门! 你说对了
OK, stop, just stop! Point made.
天啊 夏洛克
Jesus, Sherlock!
我得给我们父母打电话了 当然 他们在俄克拉荷马州
I shall have to phone our parents, of course. In Oklahoma.
这可不是你第一次因为吸毒
It won't be the first time that your substance abuse
破坏他们跳广场舞的兴致了
has wreaked havoc with their line dancing.
不是你想的那样 这是为了一个案子
This is not what you think. This is for a case.
什么案子才能解释这一切?
What case could possibly justify this?
麦努森
Magnussen.
查尔斯·奥古斯都·麦努森
Charles Augustus Magnussen.
你们刚刚可能听到了一个名字 肯定是你们听错了
That name you think you may have just heard, you were mistaken.
如果你们胆敢对外提起 在这个房间
If you ever mention hearing that name in this room,
在这样的情况下听到过这个名字
in this context, I guarantee you, on behalf
我敢以英国安全局的名义保证 你们电脑的硬盘里会出现
of the British Security Services, that materials will be found on
让你马上被监禁的文件
your computer hard-drives, resulting in your immediate incarceration.
什么都别问 做出一副被吓坏了的样子逃跑吧
Don't reply, just look frightened and scuttle.
希望我不用也这样威胁你
I hope I won't have to threaten you as well.
那样的话我们俩都会尴尬吧
Well, I think we'd both find that embarrassing.
麦努森的事和你无关
Magnussen is not your business.
- 哦 你是说他是你的了?  - 你可以把他看成是受我的保护
- Oh, you mean he's yours?  - You may consider him under my protection.
我觉得是你被他控制住了
I consider you under his thumb.
如果你胆敢跟麦努森作对
If you go against Magnussen,
那你就是在跟我过不去
then you will find yourself going against me.
好吧 我发现之后会告诉你的
OK. I'll let you know if I notice.
呃 我要说什么来着? 哦 对了
Um, what was I going to say? Oh, yeah.
拜拜
Bye-bye.
你这么做真不明智 我的弟弟
Unwise, brother mine.
哥哥...
Brother mine...
别在我嗑药之后惹我
don't appal me when I'm high.
迈克罗夫特 别说了 走吧
Mycroft, don't say another word, just go.
他能把你掰成两半 而且现在
He could snap you in two and right now,
我有点担心他真的会这么做
I'm slightly worried that he might.
什么都别说 走就是了
Don't speak, just leave.
哦
Oh.
呃 麦努森?
Er, Magnussen?
- 现在几点?  - 八点左右
- What time is it?  - About eight.
我三个小时之后得见他 我要洗个澡
I'll be meeting him in three hours. I need a bath.
- 你说这是为了一个案子?  - 是的
- It's for a case, you say?  - Yep.
什么样的案子?
What sort of a case?
任何理智的人都不愿意牵涉进这个危险的大案中来
Too big and dangerous for any sane individual to get involved in.
- 你想让我退缩?  - 才没有
- You trying to put me off?  - God, no.
是想拉你下水
Trying to recruit you.
还有 离我卧室远点
And stay out of my bedroom.
约翰 嗨 最近怎么样?
Oh, John, hi. How are you?
珍宁?
Janine?
这么衣冠不整的真是不好意思 大家都走了吗?
Sorry, not dressed. Has everybody gone?
- 我听见外面乱糟糟的  - 是啊 他们走了
- I heard shouting.  - Yes, they're gone.
天啊 这么晚了 我要迟到了
God, look at the time. I'll be late.
- 听起来是在吵架 是迈克吗?  - 迈克?
- It sounded like an argument. Was it Mike?  - Mike?
迈克 他迈克叫迈克 他们总是吵架
Mike, yeah. His brother, Mike. They're always fighting.
迈克罗夫特
Mycroft.
人们真的会这么叫他?
Do people actually call him that?
- 是啊  - 哈!
- Yeah.  - Huh!
亲 能帮我煮上咖啡吗?
Oh, could you be a love and put some coffee on?
当然 没问题
Sure, right, yeah.
谢了 玛丽怎么样? 婚后生活如何?
Thanks. Oh, how is Mary? How's married life?
她很好 我们都挺好
She's fine. We're both fine.
现在放到那边去了 夏尔呢?
Oh, it's over there now. Where's Sherl?
夏尔!
Sherl!
呃 他在洗澡 我估计他一会就出来了
Er, he's just having a bath. I'm sure he'll be out in a minute.
- 他洗澡哪里有那么快!  - 是啊
- Oh, like he ever is!  - Yeah.
早上好 还有地方容我进去吗?
Morning. Room for a little one?
早上好
Morning.
哦!
Ooh!
那么 我只是有个猜想 不过你可能有几个问题要问?
So, it's just a guess, but you've probably got some questions?
是啊 一两个 差不多吧
Yeah, one or two. Pretty much.
这很正常
Naturally.
- 你有女朋友了?  - 是啊
- You have a girlfriend?  - Yes, I have.
现在来说麦努森 他就像一条鲨鱼
Now, Magnussen. Magnussen is like a shark.
这是唯一能够形容他的动物
It's the only way I can describe him.
你去伦敦海洋馆里看过鲨鱼吗 约翰? 紧靠着玻璃那样看?
Have you ever been to the shark tank at the London Aquarium, John? Stood up close to the glass?
那些漂浮着的毫无表情的脸 空洞的眼睛 他就是那样的
Those floating, flat faces, those dead eyes. That's what he is.
我和杀人犯 精神病患者
I've dealt with murderers, psychopaths,
恐怖分子和连环杀手都交过手
terrorists, serial killers.
他们中没有任何一个人能像麦努森那样让我感到恶心
None of them can turn my stomach like Charles Augustus Magnussen.
所以你有女朋友了?
Yes, you have?
你说什么?
Sorry, what?
- 你有女朋友了?  - 什么? 是啊 是啊 我和珍宁约会了
- You have a girlfriend?  - What? Yes, yes, I'm going out with Janine.
- 我以为我做得很明显了  - 是啊 是啊
- I thought that was fairly obvious.  - Yes. Well, yes.
你... 你... 你谈恋爱了?
You... You... You are in a relationship?
是啊
Yes, I am.
- 你和珍宁?  - 嗯 是啊 我和珍宁
- You and Janine?  - Hmm. Yes, me and Janine.
能详细说说吗?
Care to elaborate?
呃 我们关系很好...
Well, we're in a good place. It's, um...
- 非常稳定  - 你从书上看来的吧
- very affirming.  - You got that from a book.
大家都是从书上看来的
Everyone got that from a book.
好啦 你们两个要乖乖的哦
OK, you two bad boys. Behave yourselves.
夏尔 你得告诉我你昨天晚上去哪了
You, Sherl, you're going to have to tell me where you were last night.
- 工作  - 工作? 好吧
- Working.  - Working? Of course.
只有我知道你是什么样的人吧 记得吗?
I'm the only one who really knows what you're like, remember?
那你可别说出去啊
Well, don't you go letting on.
那可没准
I might just, actually.
我还没告诉过玛丽这件事呢
I haven't told Mary about this.
- 我有点想给她个惊喜  - 是啊 我觉得这很有可能
- I kind of wanted to surprise her.  - Yeah, I think you probably will.
不过我们应该很快就会请你们俩来吃晚餐了
But we should have you two over for dinner, really soon.
是啊 不过得去我那 而不是在这个垃圾堆里
Yeah. My place though, not the scuzz-dump.
好啊
Great, yeah.
晚餐 真棒
Dinner, yeah.
- 我得走了 见到你真开心  - 我也是
- I'd better dash. It was brilliant to see you.  - You too.
祝你过得开心 晚点打给我
Have a lovely day. Call me later.
我应该会打给你
I might do. I might call you.
除非我遇到更帅的人
Unless I meet someone prettier.
破个案子吧 夏洛克·福尔摩斯
Solve me a crime, Sherlock Holmes.
你知道麦努森有家报社
You know Magnussen as a newspaper owner,
但他的身份远不止如此
but he is so much more than that.
他运用他的权力和财富去获取信息
He uses his power and wealth to gain information.
他得到的信息越多 他的财富和权力也会随之增加
The more he acquires, the greater his wealth and power.
毫不夸张地说 他知道西方世界每个重要人物的致命弱点
And I'm not exaggerating when I say that he knows the critical pressure point on every person of note
甚至可能不只是西方世界
or influence in the whole of the Western World and probably beyond.
他就是勒索界的拿破仑
He is the Napoleon of blackmail.
他还为那些不为人知的秘密建了一所不可攻破的堡垒
And he has created an unassailable architecture of forbidden knowledge.
叫做...
Its name...
阿普尔多尔
is Appledore.
- 晚餐?  - 不好意思 什么晚餐?
- Dinner?  - Sorry, what dinner?
我和玛丽来吃晚餐...
Me and Mary coming for dinner with...
有红酒...
wine and...
摆好座次的那种
sitting.
你在开玩笑吗? 我刚刚告诉你整个西方世界
Seriously? I have just told you that the Western World is run
- 都被这所房子控制着 而你想跟我说晚餐的事?  - 好吧 说房子吧
- from this house and you want to talk about dinner?  - Fine. Talk about the house.
这里收藏着世界上最敏感
It is the greatest repository of sensitive and dangerous
最危险的信息
information anywhere in the world,
是丑闻和秘密的亚历山大图书馆
the Alexandrian Library of secrets and scandals
而且没有任何资料是存在电脑里的
and none of it is on a computer.
他很聪明 因为电脑可以被攻破
He's smart. Computers can be hacked.
所有的信息都是纸质版 藏在这个房子的底下
It's all on hard copy, in vaults, underneath that house.
只要它还存在 你认识的任何人的隐私
And as long as it is, the personal freedom of anyone
都是无稽之谈
you've ever met is a fantasy.
门铃响了 你们听不见吗?
That was the doorbell. Couldn't you hear it?
- 是冰箱坏了 它一直响着  - 哦 可不是这个问题 夏洛克!
- It's in the fridge. It kept ringing.  - Oh, that's not a fault, Sherlock!
谁在敲门?
Who is it?
福尔摩斯先生说你们可以上楼了
Mr Holmes said you can go right up.
(玛莎·路易斯·哈德森  房东太太)
(弱点: 大麻)
哦 请吧
Oh. Go ahead.
先生?
Sir?
能稍等一下吗?
Can I have a moment?
他没问题
He's fine.
听着 我... 好吧 我可能应该告诉你...
Look, I... Right. I should probably tell you...
好吧 我...
OK, I...
就想说这个
There.
这不代表我对你不友善
Doesn't mean I'm not pleased to see you.
我可以为这个人作证 他是个医生
I can vouch for this man. He is a doctor.
如果你知道我是谁 那你也应该知道他是谁
If you know who I am, then you know who he is.
不是吗 麦努森先生?
Don't you, Mr Magnussen?
我还以为我们要在你的办公室见面
I understood we were meeting at your office.
这里就是我的办公室
This is my office.
(约翰·哈米什·华生  驻阿富汗老兵 军医)
(弱点: 哈莉·华生   玛丽·摩斯坦)
好吧 现在是了
Well, it is now.
麦努森先生 我受伊丽莎白·斯莫尔伍德女士的委托
Mr Magnussen, I have been asked to intercede with you
与您进行协商
by Lady Elizabeth Smallwood
他丈夫书信的事
on the matter of her husband's letters.
前段时间你用这些信向她施压
Some time ago you put pressure on her concerning those letters.
她希望要回这些信
She would like those letters back.
显然 这些信对你没有任何作用
Obviously, the letters no longer have any practical use to you.
所以我想...
So with that in mind...
我说错什么了?
Something I said?
没 没 我在浏览
No, no. I was reading.
真多啊
There's rather a lot.
红胡子?
Redbeard?
抱歉 抱歉 你刚才在说话
Sorry. Sorry, you were probably talking.
我...
I...
我在解释我是受托于...
I was trying to explain that I have been asked to act on behalf of...
- 洗手间在哪儿?  - 厨房旁边 先生
- Bathroom?  - Along from the kitchen, sir.
好吧 我是来协商拿回那些信的
OK. I've been asked to negotiate the return of those letters.
我明白你对敏感文件不会备份
I am aware you do not make copies of sensitive documents.
- 跟公寓其它地方一样吗?  - 什么?
- Is it like the rest of the flat?  - Sir?
浴室?
Bathroom?
- 是的 先生  - 那我还是不去了
- Yes, sir.  - Maybe not then.
允许我做其中的协调人吗?
Am I acceptable to you as an intermediary?
伊丽莎白·斯莫尔伍德女士...
Lady Elizabeth Smallwood...
我挺喜欢她的
I like her.
麦努森先生 我能
Mr Magnussen, am I acceptable to you
做中间的协调人吗?
as an intermediary?
她是有骨气的英国人
She's English with a spine.
英国人最好的一点...
Best thing about the English...
就是你们很听话
you're so domesticated.
站在那一个劲地道歉...
All standing around, apologising...
卑微地低着头
keeping your little heads down.
你可以为所欲为 没人可以阻拦你
You can do what you like here. No-one's ever going to stop you.
一群食草动物
A nation of herbivores.
我的利益集团遍布全世界...
I have interests all over the world but...
但一切都起源于英国
everything starts in England.
如果在这里奏效...
If it works here...
我就到真正的国家去试试
I try it in a real country.
大英帝国
The United Kingdom,
西方世界的培养皿
petri dish to the Western World.
告诉伊丽莎白女士 我可能会用到这些信...
Tell Lady Elizabeth I might need those letters so...
所以我留下了
I'm keeping them.
再见
Goodbye.
无论如何...
Anyway...
写得很好笑
they're funny.
天啊!
Jesus!
你发现他做了一件非常极品的事吗?
Did you notice the one extraordinary thing he did?
想忘都难 是的
There was a moment that kind of stuck in the mind, yeah.
是啊 他给我们看到了那些信
Exactly. When he showed us the letters.
所以 他把信逮到了伦敦
OK. So, he's brought the letters to London,
不管他说什么 他已经准备要完成一笔交易
so no matter what he says, he's ready to make a deal.
现在 麦努森只会在那人的弱点上交易
Now, Magnussen only makes a deal once he's established a person's weaknesses,
或者是他说的压制点 所以他坚信
the pressure point, he calls it. So, clearly he believes
我是个瘾君子 不足为惧
I'm a drug addict and no serious threat.
还有当然 他今晚七点到十点会和市场部的主管吃饭
And of course, because he's in town tonight, the letters will be in his safe in his London office
那些信就会留在办公室的保险箱里
while he's out to dinner with the Marketing Group of GB from seven till ten.
- 你怎么知道他的行程?  - 我就是知道 今晚见
- How do you know his schedule?  - Because I do. I'll see you tonight.
- 我去买点东西  - 今晚干吗?
- I've got some shopping to do.  - What's tonight?
我会短信告诉你
I'll text instructions.
- 我会发短信告诉你我有没有空  - 你有空 我查过了
- Yeah, I'll text you if I'm available.  - You are, I checked.
- 别带枪  - 我为什么要带枪?
- Don't bring a gun.  - Why would I bring a gun?
也别带刀子或者轮胎撬杆 别把别人的胳膊扭伤了
Or a knife or a tyre lever. Probably best not to do any arm-spraining,
- 晚上再看情况  - 你就那么肯定我会跟去?
- but we'll see how the night goes.  - Are you just assuming I'm coming along?
是时候出出门了 约翰 自从结婚后你长了七磅肉 光骑车是减不下去的
Time you got out of the house, John. You've put on 7lbs since you married and the cycling isn't doing it.
- 是四磅  - 玛丽和我都觉得是七磅 回见
- It's actually 4lbs.  - Mary and I think seven. See you later.
特大新闻
And breaking news now.
国会议员约翰·嘉文今天因贪污被捕
John Garvie MP has been arrested today on charges of corruption.
这引起一系列调查...
This follows an investigation...
麦努森的办公室在顶楼 就在他私人公寓下面
Magnussen's office is on the top floor, just below his private flat.
中间有十四层安保措施
There are 14 layers of security between us and him,
其中两个在英国不合法
two of which aren't even legal in this country.
- 想知道我们怎么闯进去吗?  - 我们要闯进去?
- Want to know how we're going to break in?  - Is that what we're doing?
当然
Of course it's what we're doing.
麦努森的私人电梯
Magnussen's private lift.
直通他的房间和办公室 只有他能使用
Goes straight to his penthouse and office. Only he uses it
也只有他有门禁卡
and only his keycard calls the lift.
如果其他人想要进入 会自动触发安保
If anyone else even tries, security is automatically informed.
这栋楼普通的卡
Standard keycard for the building.
昨天搞来的 最多把我们送到餐厅
Nicked it yesterday. Only gets us as far as the canteen.
就这了 如果我用这张卡刷电梯
Here we go then. If I was to use this card on that lift now,
- 会发生什么?  - 警报会响起
- what happens?  - Well, the alarms would go off
- 你会被保安拖走  - 的确
- and you'd be dragged away by security.  - Exactly.
拖进小黑屋暴打一顿
Get taken to a small room somewhere and your head kicked in.
- 那么有画面感?  - 消磨时间啊
- Do we really need so much colour?  - It passes the time.
但如果我这样...
But if I do this...
把手机和门禁卡放在一起
If you press a keycard against your mobile phone for long enough,
它就会被消磁 卡就没用了
it corrupts the magnetic strip. The card stops working.
这是常识 不要把手机和磁卡放一起
It's a common problem. Never put your keycard with your phone.
要是我用这张卡会怎么样?
What happens if I use the card now?
还是没用
It still doesn't work.
但不会显示为错卡
But it doesn't read as the wrong card now.
会显示卡被损坏了
It registers as corrupted.
如果是卡坏了 他们怎么确定不是麦努森呢?
But if it's corrupted, how do they know it's not Magnussen?
- 他们会冒险拖走他?  - 可能不会
- Would they risk dragging him off?  - Probably not.
那么他们会怎么办? 会怎么做?
So, what do they do? What do they have to do?
核实是不是他本人
Check if it's him or not.
在门右侧的视线高度有个摄像头
There's a camera at eye height to the right of the door.
用卡人的实时录像会直接传到
A live picture of the card user is relayed directly
麦努森的私人秘书那里
to Magnussen's personal staff in his office,
那是唯一能确认身份的人
the only people trusted to make a positive ID.
这个点 应该是他的私人助理
At this hour, almost certainly his PA.
那现在怎么办?
So, how does that help us?
靠人为失误
Human error.
我去购物了
I've been shopping.
我们走
Here we go then.
你长得可不像麦努森?
You realise you don't exactly look like Magnussen?
这可是大优势呢
Which in this case is a considerable advantage.
- 夏洛克 你真是疯了 你来干吗?!  - 等一下 那不是...?
- Sherlock, you complete loon. What are you doing?!  - Hang on, was that...?
你好 珍宁
Hi, Janine.
让我进去吧
Go on, let me in.
别傻了 你知道我不能放你进来
I can't. You know I can't. Don't be silly.
别让我在外面做这事
Don't make me do it out here.
在这么多人面前
Not in front of everyone.
做什么?
Do what in front of everyone?
- 你看 只要是人 都有弱点  - 那是珍宁
- You see, as long as there's people, there's always a weak spot.  - That was Janine.
当然就是她 她是麦努森的私人助理
Yes, of course it was. She's Magnussen's PA.
- 这才是关键所在  - 你因为要闯进一间办公室而订婚了?
- That's the whole point.  - Did you just get engaged to break into an office?
- 是啊 在你婚礼上认识的 有你的功劳  - 天啊!
- Yeah. Stroke of luck meeting her at your wedding. You can take some of the credit.  - Jesus!
- 夏洛克 她是爱你的  - 是啊 正如我所说 人为失误
- Sherlock, she loves you.  - Yes. Like I said, human error.
- 你要怎么办?  - 显然不可能娶她
- What are you going to do?  - Well, not actually marry her, obviously.
- 当然也不能太过分  - 那你打算怎么告诉她?
- There's only so far you can go.  - So, what will you tell her?
告诉她我是为了闯进他老板的办公室
Well, I'll tell her that our entire relationship was a ruse
才跟她在一起的 我想她会自己结束吧
to break into her boss's office. I imagine she'll want to stop
不过你才是女人方面的专家
seeing me at that point, but you're the expert on women.
她去哪了?
So, where did she go?
我刚求过婚 这也太不礼貌了
That's a bit rude. I just proposed to her.
夏洛克
Sherlock.
她高兴得晕过去了?
Did she faint?
女人真的会这样吗?!
Do they really do that?!
头被打伤了
It's a blow to the head.
她还有呼吸
She's breathing.
珍宁?
Janine?
这儿还有一个
Another in here.
是保安
Security.
他需要帮助吗?
Does he need help?
有犯罪前科 白人主义者的纹身 谁管他?
Ex-con. White supremacist by the tattoos, so who cares?
照顾好珍宁
Stick with Janine.
珍宁 听见我说话了吗?
Janine, focus on my voice. Can you hear me?
(温度: 35°C)
他们还在这
Hey, they must still be here.
麦努森也在 他椅子还是热的
So is Magnussen. His seat's still warm.
他应该在晚餐 但他现在在楼里
He should be at dinner, but he's still in the building.
- 在楼上  - 我们应该报警
- Upstairs.  - We should call the police.
我们正入室抢劫呢? 在这方面你真是没天赋啊
During our own burglary? You're really not a natural at this, are you?
等等 嘘
No, wait. Sssh.
有香水 但不是简妮的
Perfume and not Janine's.
月色 在哪闻过?
Claire de la Lune. Why do I know it?
- 玛丽就用那个  - 不 不是玛丽 另有其人
- Mary wears it.  - No, not Mary. Somebody else.
夏洛克!
Sherlock!
你丈夫会怎么想?
What would your husband think?
你可爱可敬的丈夫
Your lovely husband, upright and honourable,
那么绅士 他现在会对你说什么?
so English. What would he say to you now?
不 不!
No, no!
你做这些是为了让他不知道真相?
You're doing this to protect him from the truth?
这是他想要的吗?
Well, is this the protection he would want?
另外 如果你想要杀人
Additionally, if you're going to commit murder,
希望你换一种香水 斯莫尔伍德女士
you might consider changing your perfume, Lady Smallwood.
抱歉 谁?
Sorry. Who?
这个... 不是斯莫尔伍德女士 福尔摩斯先生
That's... not Lady Smallwood, Mr Holmes.
(骗子)
- 约翰跟你一起来了吗?  - 他 嗯...
- Is John with you?  - He's, um...
约翰在这吗?
Is John here?
他在楼下
He's downstairs.
你现在打算怎么办?
So, what do you do now?
杀了我们俩?
Kill us both?
玛丽 不管他手中有你的任何把柄 我会帮你
Mary, whatever he's got on you, let me help.
夏洛克 你再敢上前一步 我会杀了你
Oh, Sherlock, if you take one more step, I swear I will kill you.
不 华生太太...
No, Mrs Watson...
你不会
you won't.
抱歉 夏洛克
I'm sorry, Sherlock.
真的很抱歉
I truly am.
玛丽?
Mary?
这可不像在电影里
It's not like it is in the movies.
不会有血花四溅 人也不会向后飞去
There's not a great big spurt of blood and you go flying backwards.
冲击力不会扩散
The impact isn't spread over a wide area.
而是集中于一点 基本没有能量传递
It's tightly focused so there's little or no energy transfer.
你站着不动 子弹就射穿了你
You stay still and the bullet pushes through.
基本上就死定了 你得集中注意力
You're almost certainly going to die, so we need to focus.
我说了 "专心!"
I said, "Focus!"
有个记忆宫殿很好
It's all well and clever having a mind palace,
但你只有三秒钟清醒的时间
but you've only three seconds of consciousness left to use it.
所以快想 致死的原因是什么?
So, come on. What's going to kill you?
- 失血过多  - 是的 所以只有一个关键
- Blood loss.  - Exactly. So, it's all about one thing now
往前倒还是往后倒?
forwards or backwards?
我们得决定好你往哪里倒
We need to decide which way you're going to fall.
- 一个洞还是两个?  - 什么?
- One hole or two?  - Sorry?
子弹还在你体内吗? 还是射穿了?这取决于是什么枪
Is the bullet still inside you? Or is there an exit wound? It'll depend on the gun.
我想是这种
That one, I think.
或者这种
Or that one.
天啊 夏洛克 这跟枪无关
Oh, for God's sake, Sherlock. It doesn't matter about the gun.
别傻了
Don't be stupid.
你总是这么傻
You always were so stupid.
真令人失望
Such a disappointment.
我不傻
I'm not stupid.
你是个傻小子
You're a very stupid little boy.
爸妈会很生气的
Mummy and Daddy are very cross
因为这跟枪无关
because it doesn't matter about the gun.
为什么?
Why not?
你刚进房间就看了整个屋子
You saw the whole room when you entered it.
在你被谋杀前 你背后是什么?
What was directly behind you when you were murdered?
我还没死呢
I've not been murdered yet.
极有可能 小弟弟
Balance of probability, little brother.
如果子弹穿过了你 你会听见什么?
If the bullet had passed through you, what would you have heard?
玻璃碎掉的声音
The mirror shattering.
没听到 所以...?
You didn't. Therefore...?
子弹还在我体内
The bullet's still inside me.
所以要往后倒
So we need to take him down backwards.
我同意 夏洛克 你需要向后倒
I agree. Sherlock, you need to fall on your back.
现在子弹就像瓶塞一样
Right now the bullet is the cork in a bottle.
本身可以止住大部分血
The bullet itself is blocking most of the blood flow.
但是任何挤压压力都会使它错位
But any pressure or impact on the entrance wound could dislodge it.
还有 背部着地 重力也能止血
Plus, on your back, gravity's working for us.
现在...
Fall...
倒下吧
now.
怎么回事?! 发生什么事了?!
What the hell is that?! What's happening?!
你会进入休克 这是下一个致死的原因
You're going into shock. It's the next thing that's going to kill you.
- 我该早呢么做?  - 很明显 别休克就行
- What do I do?  - Don't go into shock, obviously.
你这个可笑的记忆宫殿里肯定有
Must be something in this ridiculous memory palace of yours
能让你冷静下来的东西
that can calm you down.
找到它
Find it.
东风神要来了 夏洛克
The East Wind is coming, Sherlock.
他要来抓你了
It's coming to get you.
找到它
Find it.
你好呀 红胡子 快过来
Hello, Redbeard. Here, boy.
来 来我这儿
Come on. Come to me.
来吧 没事的
It's OK. It's all right.
快过来 是我呀
Come on. It's me. It's me.
过来
Come on.
好孩子 真聪明
Good boy. Clever boy.
好孩子
Good boy.
你好呀 红胡子 他们也要杀了我了
Hello, Redbeard. They're putting me down too now.
这真没劲 是吧?
It's no fun, is it?
红胡子
Redbeard.
休克过去了 你会感觉到疼痛
That was shock. You're going to feel the pain.
你身上开了个洞
There's a hole ripped through you.
严重内出血
Massive internal bleeding.
你得控制疼痛感
You have to control the pain.
控制 控制 控制
Control. Control. Control.
你...
You...
你从来感觉不到疼痛 对吧?
you never felt pain, did you?
你怎么会感觉不到的?
Why did you never feel pain?
你总是能感觉到 夏洛克
You always feel it, Sherlock.
但你不必惧怕它
But you don't have to fear it!
疼痛...
Pain...
心碎...
heartbreak...
失去...
loss...
死亡...
death...
都是好事
it's all good.
全都是好事
It's all good.
夏洛克! 夏洛克 能听到我说话吗?
Sherlock! Sherlock. Can you hear me?
出了什么事?
What happened?
他中枪了
He got shot.
天啊!
Jesus!
夏洛克
Sherlock.
天啊!
Oh, my!
谁开的枪?!
Who shot him?!
应急中心 您需要什么服务?
Emergency. Which service do you require?
∮ 下雨了 ∮
∮ It's raining ∮
∮ 大雨了 ∮
∮ It's pouring ∮
∮ 夏洛克无聊了 ∮
∮ Sherlock is boring ∮
∮ 我笑了 ∮
∮ I'm laughing ∮
∮ 我哭了 ∮
∮ I'm crying ∮
∮ 夏洛克要死了 ∮
∮ Sherlock is dying ∮
夏洛克!
Sherlock!
坚持住 夏洛克!
We're losing you. Sherlock!
来吧 夏洛克 乖乖死掉 好吗?
Come on, Sherlock. Just die, why can't you?
小小推一把
One little push
你就死透了
and off you pop.
你会喜欢死去的感觉的 夏洛克 没人会再烦你
You're going to love being dead, Sherlock. No-one ever bothers you.
哈德森太太会哭...
Mrs Hudson will cry...
爸爸妈妈会哭...
and Mummy and Daddy will cry...
那个女人会哭 约翰会哭得特别伤心
and the woman will cry and John will cry buckets and buckets.
我最担心的就是他了 他那个老婆!
It's him that I worry about the most. That wife!
你让他失望了 夏洛克
You're letting him down, Sherlock.
约翰·华生肯定有危险了
John Watson is definitely in danger.
好像没让你好受点 是吧?
Oh, you're not getting better, are you?
是因为我说的话吗?
Was it something I said, huh?
夏洛克!
Sherlock!
- 玛丽  - 嘿
- Mary.  - Hey.
他刚刚才醒过来
He's only bloody woken up.
他挺过来了
He's pulled through.
- 真的?  - 真的
- Really?  - Yeah.
- 真的?  - 你...
- Seriously?  - You...
华生太太 你有大麻烦了
Mrs Watson, you're in big trouble.
真的? 怎么了?
Really? Why?
他醒过来说的第一个词...
His first word when he woke up...
就是"玛丽"
"Mary."
别告诉他
You don't tell him.
夏洛克?
Sherlock?
别告诉约翰
You don't tell John.
坏姑娘
Bad girl.
真是个坏姑娘
Bad, bad girl.
看着我...
Look at me...
说你不会告诉他的
and tell me you're not going to tell him.
我要买一间小屋
I'm buying a cottage.
我靠你赚了很多钱 先生
I've made a lot of money out of you, mister.
没有比一边报复一边赚钱更爽的了
Nothing hits the spot like revenge with profits.
你没把这些告诉麦努森吧?
You didn't give those stories to Magnussen, did you?
当然没有 是他的竞争对手 他可不屑这些
God, no. One of his rivals. He was spitting.
恩
Hmm.
夏洛克·福尔摩斯 你真是个阴险狡诈 没心没肺
Sherlock Holmes, you are a back-stabbing, heartless,
满嘴谎言的混蛋
manipulative bastard.
事实证明 你是个贪婪 投机取巧
And you, as it turns out, are a grasping, opportunistic,
渴望出名的小报婊子
publicity-hungry, tabloid whore.
那我们扯平了?
So, we're good then?
是的 当然
Yeah, of course.
- 小屋在哪儿?  - 苏塞克斯当斯
- Where's the cottage?  - Sussex Downs.
- 挺好  - 很漂亮
- Nice.  - It's gorgeous.
那里有蜂巢 但我打算清理掉
There's beehives, but I'm getting rid of those.
伤口很疼 是吧?
Oh, it hurts, does it?
你最好还是接着注射吗啡
Probably want to restart your morphine.
我摆弄了一下开关
I might have fiddled with the taps.
- 你需要报复多少才能满足?  - 偶尔补充一下就够了
- How much more revenge are you going to need?  - Just the occasional top-up.
这地方对你来说还真是梦想成真了
Dream come true for you, this place.
他们真的给你注射毒品了
They actually attach the drugs to you.
这对工作不利
Not good for working.
你得停工一段时间了 夏尔
You won't be working for a while, Sherl.
你骗了我
You lied to me.
一骗再骗
You lied and lied.
我利用了我们对彼此的好感
I exploited the fact of our connection.
什么时候?
When?
哪怕说一次实话也就够了
Just once would have been nice.
噢
Oh.
我本打算结婚的时候再说的
I was waiting till we got married.
我们永远结不了婚
That was never going to happen.
我得走了
Got to go.
我不应该让你一直说话
I'm not supposed to keep you talking.
而且我要在一台的节目接受采访
And also, I have an interview with The One Show
还没准备好呢
and I haven't made it up yet.
再说一句...
Just one thing...
你不应该骗我的
you shouldn't have lied to me.
我知道你为人如何
I know what kind of man you are,
但我们本可以做朋友的
but we could have been friends.
我会代你向约翰和玛丽问好的
I'll give your love to John and Mary.
别告诉他
You don't tell him.
别告诉约翰
You don't tell John.
所以...
So...
玛丽·华生...
Mary Watson...
你到底是谁?
who are you?
玛丽·华生
Mary Watson.
我不知道你能听懂多少他说的话
I don't know how much sense you'll get out of him.
他被注射了药物 说话很含糊
He's drugged up, so he's pretty much babbling.
他们不会允许你在医院里打电话的 懂吗?
Oh, they won't let you use that in here, you know?
我不会打电话 只是想拍段视频
No, I'm not going to use the phone. I just want to take a video.
天啊!
Oh, Jesus!
他会去哪儿?
So, where would he go?
天知道!
Oh, Christ knows!
要在伦敦找夏洛克
Try finding Sherlock in London.
他有三个已知的避难所
He's got three known bolt-holes.
议会山 康顿水门和达格玛法院
Parliament Hill, Camden Lock and Dagmar Court.
五个已知的避难所
Five known bolt holes.
基尤皇家植物园的盲人温室
There's the blind greenhouse in Kew Gardens
汉普斯特得公墓的墓室
and the leaning tomb in Hampstead Cemetery.
空卧室
Just the spare bedroom.
是我的卧室
Well, my bedroom.
我们都同意他需要空间
We agreed he needs the space.
大本钟钟面的后面
Behind the clock face of Big Ben.
我想他大概是在开玩笑
I think he was probably joking.
不 我觉得是真的
No, I don't think so.
伦斯特花园 这是他首选的避难所 非常机密
Leinster Gardens. It's his number one bolt hole. Top, top secret.
他有天晚上跟踪他的时候才知道的
He only knows about it cos he stalked him one night.
- 跟着!  - 是跟着
- Followed!  - Followed, yeah.
他知道是谁开的枪
He knew who shot him.
伤口在正面 所以他当时面对着凶手
The bullet wound was here, so he was facing whoever it was.
为什么不告诉我们? 因为他正在独自追查凶手
So, why not tell us? Because he's tracking them down himself.
- 或是在保护他们  - 保护凶手 为什么?
- Or protecting them.  - Protecting the shooter, why?
那就是在保护某人 但他为什么在乎?
Well, protecting someone then. But why would he care?
他是夏洛克 有谁是他想保护的吗?
He's Sherlock. Who would he bother protecting?
有事情就打我电话 不要慢着我 约翰
Call me if you hear anything. Don't hold out on me, John.
- 打给我 好吗?  - 好 知道了
- Call me, OK?  - Yeah. Yeah, right.
- 晚安  - 再见
- Good night then.  - Bye then.
约翰 想喝杯茶吗?
John, need a cuppa?
哈德森太太 夏洛克怎么就认为我会搬回来呢?
Mrs Hudson, why does Sherlock think that I'll be moving back in here?
当然 他把你的椅子放回去了 不是吗?
Oh, yes, he's put your chair back again, hasn't he?
很不错 看上去更好看了
That's nice. It looks much better.
约翰 怎么了? 跟我说说 约翰?
John, what's wrong? Tell me. John?
是你的电话 对吧?
That's your phone, isn't it?
是夏洛克 约翰 是夏洛克打来的
It's Sherlock, John. Sherlock.
约翰 你得接电话!
John, you have to answer it!
- 给点零钱吧 女士  - 不行  - 求你了
- Spare any change, love?  - No.  - Oh, come on, love.
别和其他人一样
Don't be like all the rest.
规矩一 想找夏洛克·福尔摩斯 必须是他先找上你
Rule one of looking for Sherlock Holmes, he finds you.
你现在为夏洛克工作了吗?
You're working for Sherlock now?
- 至少我不会在街上乱逛了 对吧?  - 不是吧
- Keeps me off the streets, doesn't it?  - Well... no.
- 你在哪儿?  - 你看不到我吗?
- Where are you?  - Can't you see me?
我要找什么?
Well, what am I looking for?
伦斯特花园的谎言 就在你眼前
The lie, the lie of Leinster Gardens, hidden in plain sight.
别人看不见 在这儿长住的人们却总是看不见
Hardly anyone notices. People live here for years and never see it.
但如果我猜的没错 你一分钟就能发现
But if you are what I think you are, it will take you less than a minute.
房子 玛丽 看看房子
The houses, Mary. Look at the houses.
你怎么知道我会来?
How did you know I'd come here?
我知道你会去和别人忽视的人谈话
I knew you'd talk to the people no-one else would bother with.
我以为那只是小聪明
Huh, I thought I was being clever.
你一直很聪明 玛丽 我靠的就是这点
You're always clever, Mary, I was relying on that.
我留下线索 让你寻找
I planted the information for you to find.
哦!
Ohh!
只用了30秒
30 seconds.
但这是什么?
But what am I looking at?
没有门把手 没有信箱 窗户被刷上了油漆
No door knobs, no letterbox. Painted windows.
伦斯特花园23号和24号
23 and 24 Leinster Gardens.
空置的房子
The empty houses.
为了给伦敦地下铁腾地方 为老式蒸汽火车造通风口
They were demolished years ago to make way for the London Underground,
房子很久前就被拆毁了
a vent for the old steam trains.
只有房子最靠前的部分保留了下来
Only the very front section of the house remains.
只是个假象
It's just a facade.
有没有让你想到谁 玛丽?
Remind you of anyone, Mary?
假象?
A facade?
抱歉 我总是忍不住弄出点戏剧效果
Sorry, I never could resist a touch of drama.
请进吧 里面有点窄
Do come in. It's a little cramped.
你是这地方的主人吗?
Do you own this place?
我和克拉伦斯府的人大牌赢来的
Hmm, I won it in a card game with the Clarence House Cannibal.
差点害我失去了肾 但幸运的是 我拿到了同花顺
Nearly cost me my kidneys, but fortunately I had a straight flush.
那女人赌劲十足
Quite a gambler, that woman.
你想要什么 夏洛克?
What do you want, Sherlock?
玛丽·摩斯坦夭折 死于1972年10月
Mary Morstan was stillborn in October 1972.
她的墓碑在奇斯威克公墓 五年前
Her gravestone is in Chiswick cemetery, where five years ago
你得到了她的名字和生日 之后便用她的身份生活
you acquired her name and date of birth, and thereafter her identity.
所以你在那之前没有朋友
That's why you don't have friends from before that date.
得好好想想你那边的客人 玛丽 看上去有点少
Need to work on your half of the church, Mary. Looking a bit thin.
孤儿没什么其它东西 我也就只有这些朋友了
Oh, orphan's lot. Friends, that's all I have.
这对某些人来说是非常老旧的手段了
It's an old enough technique, known to the kinds of people
他们能一眼看出跳步码...
who could recognise a skip code on sight...
一开始我以为是圣经里的内容 垃圾广告 但不是的
At first I thought it was just a Bible thing, spam, but it's not.
是跳步码
It's a skip code.
有超强的记忆能力
Have extraordinarily retentive memories.
你怎么会记不得哪个房间? 你过目不忘啊!
How can you not remember which room? You remember everything!
- 我得清理内存!  - 是207
- I have to delete something!  - 207.
你太慢了
You were very slow.
你的枪法如何?
How good a shot are you?
你有多想知道?
How badly do you want to find out?
如果我死在这里 他们就会发现我的尸体
If I die here, my body would be found in a building
在一栋外墙有你照片的楼里
with your face projected on the front of it.
哪怕是苏格兰场的人都能查出问题
Even Scotland Yard could get somewhere with that.
我想知道你的枪法有多好
I want to know how good you are.
快点 给我看看
Go on, show me.
医生的妻子现在肯定有点无聊了
The doctor's wife must be a little bit bored by now.
我能看看吗?
May I see?
那是个仿制品
Huh, it's a dummy.
我想这把戏还真是明显
Well, I suppose that was a fairly obvious trick.
但当时只隔了六步
And yet, over a distance of six feet,
你却没能一枪杀了我
you failed to make a kill shot.
你让我躺进了医院 却没能杀我
Enough to hospitalise me, not enough to kill me.
那不是失手 是故意为之
That wasn't a miss, that was surgery.
- 我接下这案子了  - 什么案子?
- I'll take the case.  - What case?
你的案子 你为什么不一开始就冲我来?
Yours. Why didn't you come to me in the first place?
因为不能让约翰知道我骗了他
Because John can't ever know that I lied to him.
这会让他伤心 我就永远失去他了
It would break him and I would lose him forever.
夏洛克 我不会让这种事情发生的
And Sherlock, I will never let that happen.
所以请你明白
Please, understand,
为了阻止这种事情发生 没有事情是我不会做的
there is nothing in this world I would not do to stop that happening.
抱歉
Sorry.
这把戏还不够明显
Not that obvious a trick.
去和他谈谈 快点把事情解决
Now talk and sort it out and do it quickly.
∮ 听! 天使在唱歌 ∮
∮ Hark! The Herald Angels Sing ∮
天啊 竟然只有两点
Oh, dear God, it's only two o'clock.
至少都已经过了一周的圣诞节了
It's been Christmas Day for at least a week now.
怎么可能只有两点? 我快死了
How can it only be two o'clock? I'm in agony.
迈克 这是你的笔记本电脑吗?
Mikey, is this your laptop?
上面的资料决定了自由世界的安全 是我的
Upon which depends the security of the free world, yes,
你还把土豆放在了上面!
and you've got potatoes on it!
如果真有那么重要 你就不应该随便放
You shouldn't leave it lying around if it's so important.
我们为什么要这么做? 我们从不庆祝
Why are we doing this? We never do this.
因为夏洛克出院回家了
We are here because Sherlock is home from hospital
我们都很高兴
and we are all very happy.
我也高兴吗? 我怎么不知道
Am I happy too? I haven't checked.
礼貌点 迈克!
Behave, Mike!
你给我起的名字叫迈克罗夫特
Mycroft is the name you gave me,
- 你最好坚持一直这么叫下去  - 福尔摩斯夫人
- if you could possibly struggle all the way to the end.  - Mrs Holmes.
谢谢 亲爱的 我不知道你为什么会来这儿
Oh, thank you, dear. I'm not absolutely sure why you're here.
我邀请他的
I invited him.
我是他的门徒 福尔摩斯夫人
I'm his protege, Mrs Holmes.
他死后 我会得到他的一切 还有工作
When he dies, I get all his stuff and his job.
- 不对  - 好吧 我就是帮点忙
- No.  - Oh, well, I help out a bit.
这话靠谱些了
Closer.
如果他被谋杀什么的了...
If he does get murdered or something...
- 你还是闭嘴好了  - 好吧
- Probably stop talking now.  - OK.
你能带朋友来真是太好了!
Lovely when you bring your friends round!
不要欺负他了 有人对我儿子开了一枪
Stop it, you. Somebody's put a bullet in my boy.
如果让我知道是谁 我肯定就会发狂去报复
If I ever find out who, I shall turn absolutely monstrous.
这是给玛丽的 我一会儿就回来
This was for Mary. I'll be back in a minute.
(倒计时: 7分37秒)
玛丽 你在这儿呀
Ah. Mary. There you are.
喝杯茶 如果老头子开始哼哼了
Cup of tea. If Father starts making little humming noises,
就给他点柴火 通常很有用
just give him a little poke. That usually does it.
这是你写的吗?
Did you write this?
年轻的时候随便写的 你就不该看的
Oh, that silly old thing, you mustn't read that.
现在看来 数学肯定很蠢
Mathematics must seem terribly fatuous now.
你别哼哼
No humming, you.
我妻子虽然总是东拉西扯 但却是个天才
Complete flake, my wife, but happens to be a genius.
她是个数学家?
She was a mathematician?
为了孩子都放弃了 我从来都不敢和她吵
Gave it all up for children. I could never bear to argue with her.
因为我有点笨
I'm something of a moron myself.
但她... 性感得难以置信
But she's... unbelievably hot.
天啊 你是唯一正常的 对吧?
Oh my God, you're the sane one, aren't you?
你呢?
Aren't you?
抱歉 我只是...
Oh. Sorry, I just, er...
你们需要谈谈吗?
Oh, you two need a moment?
能否回避一下?
If you don't mind?
当然可以 我去看看能不能帮忙...
No, course not. I'll go and see if I can help with...
随便帮点忙
something or another.
他们两个 没事吧?
Those two. They all right?
要知道 婚姻总有起落
Well, you know, they've had their ups and downs.
现在回贝克街吧
Baker Street, now.
约翰 玛丽...
John, Mary...
夏洛克 天啊 你看上去糟透了!
Oh, Sherlock, oh, good gracious, you look terrible!
从你的厨房帮我拿些吗啡来 我的吃完了
Get me some morphine from your kitchen, I've run out.
- 我没有吗啡  - 那你到底想说什么?!
- I don't have any morphine.  - Then what exactly is the point of you?!
出了什么事?
What is going on?
真是个好问题
Bloody good question.
华生夫妇要进行一次家庭谈话 我希望能快点 因为还有工作要做
The Watsons are about to have a domestic and fairly quickly I hope, because we've got work to do.
不 我有个更好的问题...
No, I have a better question...
我遇到过的人都是疯子吗?
is everyone I have ever met a psychopath?
是的
Yes.
- 很好 我们回答了这个问题 现在...  - 闭嘴!
- Good that we've settled that. Now we...  - Shut up!
别说话 因为这不好笑
And stay shut up, because this is not funny.
这次一点都不好笑
Not this time.
- 我没说这很好笑  - 你
- I didn't say it was funny.  - You.
我做了什么? 嗯?
What have I ever done? Hmm?
你要毁了我整个人生?
My whole life, to deserve you?
所有一切
Everything.
夏洛克 我说过了 闭嘴
Sherlock, I've told you, shut up.
不 我说真的... 是所有一切
No, I mean it... seriously, everything.
你所做的一切 都是既成事实
Everything you've ever done, is what you did.
夏洛克 你再说一个字 我就揍晕你
Sherlock, one more word and you will not need morphine.
你是去过战场的医生
You were a doctor who went to war.
你是个不能安安分分住在郊区的人
You're a man who couldn't stay in the suburbs for more than a month
总会去袭击贼窝 揍瘾君子一顿
without storming a crack den, beating up a junkie.
你最好的朋友是个反社会者 为了不嗑药
Your best friend is a sociopath, who solves crimes
他改行破案 顺便说一句 那就是我
as an alternative to getting high. That's me, by the way, hello.
哪怕是房东太太也曾经领导过一个贩毒集团
Even the landlady used to run a drug cartel.
那是我丈夫的 我只是负责打字
It was my husband's cartel. I was just typing.
还跳艳舞
And exotic dancing.
夏洛克·福尔摩斯 如果你看YouTube...
Sherlock Holmes, if you've been YouTubing...
约翰 你对某种生活方式上瘾了
John, you are addicted to a certain lifestyle.
你不正常 危险的情况和人总是找上你
You are abnormally attracted to dangerous situations and people,
所以你发现爱上的女人也符合这个模式
so is it truly such a surprise that the woman you fall in love with
真的需要那么惊讶吗?
conforms to that pattern?
但她不应该是那样的?
But she wasn't supposed to be like that!
她为什么是那样的?
Why is she like that?
因为你选了她
Because you chose her.
为什么所有一切
Why is everything always
都是我的错?!
my fault?!
小心邻居投诉!
Oh, neighbours!
约翰 听着 冷静下来 回答我的问题
John, listen. Be calm and answer me.
她是什么?
What is she?
- 我撒谎的妻子?  - 不 她是什么?
- My lying wife?  - No, what is she?
怀着我的孩子 从相遇开始就骗我的女人?
And the woman who is carrying my child, who has lied to me since the day I met her.
不 在这间公寓 在这间房间里就不是
No. Not in this flat, not in this room.
现在在这里 她是什么?
Right here, right now, what is she?
好吧
OK.
用你的方法解决
Your way.
一向如此
Always your way.
坐
Sit.
为什么?
Why?
因为他们都做这里
Because that's where they sit.
那些来这里讲述故事的人
The people who come in here with their stories.
他们是客户 你现在也是 玛丽
They're the clients, that's all you are now, Mary.
你是个客户
You're a client.
就应该坐在这里诉说 而我们会坐在这里倾听
This is where you sit and talk and this is where we sit and listen.
然后决定要不要接你的案子
Then we decide if we want you or not.
你没事吧?
So, are you OK?
我们今天终于要交谈了吗? 还真的是圣诞节呢!
Oh, are we doing conversation today? It really is Christmas!
现在?
Now?
说真的 我们冷战了几个月 现在要谈这个?
Seriously, months of silence and we're going to do this now?
AGRA是什么?
A.G.R.A., what's that?
呃... 我名字的缩写
Er... my initials.
我原来的那些事情全在上面
Everything about who I was is on there.
如果你爱我 就不要当面看
If you love me, don't read it in front of me.
为什么?
Why?
因为你看完之后就不会爱我了
Because you won't love me when you've finished
我不想看着这事发生
and I don't want to see that happen.
你知道多少了?
How much do you know already?
根据你的技术 以前应该是情报局探员
By your skill set, you are, or were, an intelligence agent.
你现在的口音是英音 但我怀疑你不是英国人
Your accent is currently English, but I suspect you are not.
你在逃避某些事情
You're on the run from something.
你用了自己的技术搞失踪
You've used your skills to disappear.
麦努森知道你的秘密 所以你要杀了他
Magnussen knows your secret, which is why you were going to kill him.
我猜你和珍宁做朋友 就是为了接近他
And I assume you befriended Janine in order to get close to him.
你说得没错!
Oh, you can talk!
看看你们俩 你们才应该结婚
Oh, look at you two, you should have got married.
麦努森掌握的那些秘密
The stuff Magnussen has on me,
可能我下半辈子就得坐牢
I would go to prison for the rest of my life.
- 所以你就要杀了他?  - 像麦努森这样的人就应该死
- So you were going to kill him?  - People like Magnussen should be killed,
- 所以才会有像我这样的人  - 很好!
- that's why there are people like me.  - Perfect!
那你是做什么的 杀手? 我怎么没发现呢?
So that's what you were, an assassin? How could I not see that?
你发现了
You did see that.
还娶了我
And you married me.
因为他说对了
Because he's right.
你就喜欢这些
It's what you like.
玛丽 所以麦努森手上一切
So, Mary, any documents that Magnussen has
关于你的文件 你都想要收回
concerning yourself, you want extracted and returned.
你为什么要帮我?
Why would you help me?
因为你救了我的命
Because you saved my life.
抱歉... 你说什么?
Sorry... sorry, what?
当我发现你和麦努森的时候...
When I happened on you and Magnussen...
你便有了麻烦
you had a problem.
再说具体点 就是有了目击证人
More specifically, you had a witness.
你现在打算怎么办?
What do you do now?
杀了我们俩?
Kill both of us?
解决方法很简单 就是杀了我们俩 然后离开
The solution, of course, was simple. Kill us both and leave.
然而 当时你感情用事了
However, sentiment got the better of you.
用精确计算好的一枪让我失去行动力
One precisely calculated shot to incapacitate me,
希望能换取时间跟我谈判 让我对你的事保持沉默
in the hope that it would buy you more time to negotiate my silence.
当然 你不能杀麦努森
Of course, you couldn't shoot Magnussen.
那天晚上我们都潜入了大楼
On the night both of us broke into the building,
你的丈夫就会变成嫌疑犯 所以...
your own husband would become a suspect. So...
你觉得麦努森会利用你在场这件事...
you calculated that Magnussen would use the fact of your involvement...
而不会告诉警方 这就是他的风格
rather than sharing the information with the police, as is his MO.
然后你按照进去的方式离开了
And then you left the way you came.
我漏了什么吗?
Have I missed anything?
她怎么救了你的命?
How did she save your life?
- 她打电话叫了救护车  - 是我打的电话
- She phoned the ambulance.  - I phoned the ambulance.
她先打的
She phoned first.
应急中心 您需要什么服务?
Emergency, which service do you require?
你隔了五分钟才找到我的
You didn't find me for another five minutes.
如果靠你的话 我就死定了
Left to you, I would have died.
伦敦救护车的平均到场时间是...
The average arrival time for a London ambulance is...
有人叫了救护车吗?
Did somebody call an ambulance?
八分钟 你们带了吗啡吗? 我在电话里说了要带的
Eight minutes. Did you bring any morphine? I asked on the phone.
说是发生了枪击案
We were told there was a shooting.
没错 上周发生的
There was, last week.
但我觉得我内出血了
But I believe I'm bleeding internally,
我的脉搏很不规律 也许在送医院的路上得给我心肺复苏...
my pulse is very erratic, you may need to restart my heart on the way...
天啊 夏洛克 撑住 夏洛克
Jesus, Sherlock. Come on, Sherlock.
约翰 约翰 麦努森才是我们要对付的人
John, John, Magnussen is all that matters now.
你可以相信玛丽... 她救了我的命
You can trust Mary... she saved my life.
但她向你开了枪
She shot you.
但那是救我 我保证... 啊!
Mixed messages, I grant you that... Argh!
夏洛克! 夏洛克! 扶着他
Sherlock! Sherlock! Take him.
- 扶好了?  - 嗯
- Got him?  - Yeah.
你看过内容了吗?
So, have you read it?
- 可以过来一下吗?  - 不 直接说吧 你看过了吗?
- Would you come here a moment?  - No, tell me, have you?
就... 过来一下
Just... come here.
我没事
No, I'm fine.
我想了很久 该怎么和你说
I've thought long and hard about what I want to say to you.
这是我想好的话 玛丽
These are prepared words, Mary.
- 我很用心准备的  - 好的
- I've chosen these words with care.  - OK.
你过去的错 已经过去
The problems of your past are your business.
你的未来...
The problems of your future...
才是我所在乎的
are my privilege.
这就是我要说的一切
It's all I have to say, it's all I need to know.
我没看内容
No, I didn't read it.
你都不知道我的真名
You don't even know my name.
你喜欢"玛丽·沃特森"这个名字吗?
Is "Mary Watson" good enough for you?
是的 我喜欢
Yes. Oh my God, yes.
我也很喜欢这个名字
Then it's good enough for me, too.
但是这样并不表明我不生你的气了
All this does not mean that I'm not still basically pissed off with you.
嗯 我知道
Hmm, I know, I know.
我还是很生气 有时候会发火
I am very pissed off, and it will come out now and then.
我明白 我明白
I know, I know, I know.
以后你可以修剪草坪
You can mow the sodding lawn from now on.
- 我来修剪  - 我来搬运
- I do mow the lawn.  - I do it loads.
你才不会干呢
You really don't.
孩子名字我来起
I choose the baby's name.
- 那可不行  - 好吧
- Not a chance.  - OK.
- 你放弃了和麦努森的交易 我很高兴  - 是吗?
- I'm glad you've given up on the Magnussen business.  - Are you?
但我仍然很好奇 他的谜题和你以前遇到的那些不同
I'm still curious, though. He's hardly your usual kind of puzzle.
你为什么那么恨他?
Why do you hate him?
因为他欺凌不同的人
Because he attacks people who are different
用他们的秘密威胁他们 你不恨吗?
and preys on their secrets. Why don't you?
他从来没找过大人物的麻烦
He never causes too much damage to anyone important.
这一点很明智
He's far too intelligent for that.
他只是个商人 有时候对我们还有用
He's a businessman, that's all. And occasionally useful to us.
他是有点小邪恶 但不是待戮的龙
A necessary evil, not a dragon for you to slay.
戮龙骑士 你就是这么看我的?
A dragon-slayer. Is that what you think of me?
不 你自己这么看待自己的
No. It's what you think of yourself.
你们俩在抽烟?!
Are you two smoking?!
- 没有  - 是迈克罗夫特抽的
- No.  - It was Mycroft.
我有个职位邀请 希望你能拒绝
I have, by the way, a job offer I should like you to decline.
我拒绝你的好意
I decline your kind offer.
我会传达你的歉意的
I shall pass on your regrets.
- 什么职位?  - 军情六处想让你回东欧
- What was it?  - MI6. They want to place you back into Eastern Europe.
要冒着生命危险执行卧底任务
An undercover assignment that would prove fatal to you in,
大约六个月
I think, about six months.
那你为什么还希望我拒绝?
Then why don't you want me to take it?
我很想让你去 但是权衡之后 觉得还是留着你更有用
It's tempting, but on balance, you have more utility closer to home.
有用! 我有什么用?
Utility! How do I have utility?
当龙
Here be dragons.
我抽不惯这烟
This isn't agreeing with me.
先进去了
I'm going in.
你要抽低焦油的烟 你还像刚开始抽烟一样
You need low tar. You still smoke like a beginner.
还有...
Also...
失去你我会伤心欲绝的
your loss would break my heart.
你要我怎么接话?!
What the hell am I supposed to say to that?!
- 说句"圣诞快乐"?  - 你讨厌圣诞节的
- Merry Christmas?  - You hate Christmas.
是啊 也许是甜酒里被下了什么药
Yes. Perhaps there was something in the punch.
有道理 多喝点
Clearly. Go and have some more.
夏洛克让我们见他的父母 是有什么用意?
So you realise that Sherlock got us out here to see his mum and dad for a reason?
他的父母婚姻很幸福 我明白他的用心
His lovely mum and dad, a fine example of married life, I get that.
夏洛克就是这样 总是出其不意
That is the thing with Sherlock, it's always the unexpected.
嘿? 玛丽?
Oi. Oi? Mary?
天啊! 玛丽? 快坐下
Jesus Christ! Mary? Sit down.
玛丽 能听见我说话吗?
Mary, can you hear me?
别喝玛丽的茶
Don't drink Mary's tea.
或她的甜酒
Or the punch.
夏洛克...
Sherlock...
你给我怀孕的妻子下药了?!
did you just drug my pregnant wife?!
不用担心 维金斯是个出色的药剂师
Don't worry, Wiggins is an excellent chemist.
我亲自给你妻子下的药量 不会有一点伤害的
I calculated your wife's dose myself. Won't affect the little one.
我会照顾好她的
I'll keep an eye on her.
他会等着他们醒来 这本来就是做这工作的
He'll monitor their recovery. It's more or less his day job.
你到底在干吗?!
What the hell have you done?!
与恶魔交易
A deal with the devil.
你怎么不在医院里?
Shouldn't you be in hospital?
这里就是医院 医院食堂
I am in hospital. This is the canteen.
- 是吗?  - 我觉得是 请坐
- Is it?  - In my opinion, yes. Have a seat.
谢谢
Thank you.
我正想到你呢
I've been thinking about you.
我也正在想你
是吗?
Really?
我想看看阿普尔多尔
I want to see Appledore.
你把所有秘密 所有文件
Where you keep all the secrets, all the files,
所有要挟别人的证据都藏在那里
everything you've got on everyone.
希望你能邀请我去看看
I want you to invite me.
为什么你觉得我会那么不谨慎?
What makes you think I'd be so careless?
哦 我觉得你比看起来更粗心
Oh, I think you're a lot more careless than you let on.
我有吗?
Am I?
呆滞的眼神泄露了你的秘密
It's the dead-eyed stare that gives it away.
除非那并不是呆滞 对吗?
Except it's not dead-eyed, is it?
你一直在阅读
You're reading.
便携式阿普尔多尔 怎么个情况?
Portable Appledore. How does it work?
植入式硬盘? 4G无线网?
Built-in flash drive? 4G wireless?
这只是普通的眼镜
They're just ordinary spectacles.
是的 没错
Yes, they are.
(弱点: 吗啡)
你低估我了 福尔摩斯先生
You underestimate me, Mr Holmes.
那你让我看看你的真本事 让我看看阿普尔多尔
Impress me, then. Show me Appledore.
每件东西都有代价
Everything is available for a price.
你用什么来交换?
Are you making me an offer?
圣诞礼物
A Christmas present.
你会送我什么作为圣诞礼物 福尔摩先生?
And what are you giving me for Christmas, Mr Holmes?
我哥哥
My brother.
天啊!
Oh, Jesus!
夏洛克 请你快告诉我你没疯
Sherlock, please tell me you haven't just gone out of your mind.
你还是自己猜吧
I'd rather keep you guessing.
啊 飞机来了
Ah, there's our lift.
一起去吗?
Coming?
去哪?
Where?
- 你想让你妻子平安无事吗?  - 我当然想了
- You want your wife to be safe?  - Of course I do.
太好了 因为这件事非常的危险
Good, because this is going to be incredibly dangerous.
稍有差错 就会违反英国安全法 就会因叛国罪
One false move and we'll have betrayed the security of the United Kingdom and be in prison
去蹲监狱 麦努森是我们遇到的最难缠的对手
for high treason. Magnussen is the most dangerous man we've ever encountered
成败都在此一举
and the odds are comprehensively stacked against us.
- 今天可是圣诞节!  - 确实很有节日气氛
- But it's Christmas!  - I feel the same.
哦 你说的是真正的圣诞节 你听我的话 带上枪了吗?
Oh, you mean it's actually Christmas. Did you bring your gun, as I suggested?
去你父母家参加圣诞节宴会为什么要带枪?
Why would I bring my gun to your parents' house for Christmas dinner?!
- 在大衣口袋里?  - 是的
- Is it in your coat?  - Yes.
- 那我们出发吧  - 出发去哪?
- Off we go, then.  - Where are we going?
去阿普尔多尔
Appledore.
你们也来一杯吧 这可是上等好酒
I would offer you a drink, but it's very rare and expensive.
原来是你策划的
Oh, it was you.
当然是我
Yes, of course.
我发现想要找到你的弱点真不容易 福尔摩斯先生
Very hard to find a pressure point on you, Mr Holmes.
我可从来不信你有毒瘾这事
The drugs thing I never believed for a moment.
但就算暴露了 你也不在乎 是吧?
Anyway, you wouldn't care if it was exposed, would you?
但你真的很在乎约翰·华生
But look how you care about John Watson.
待解救的小女孩
Your damsel in distress.
为了威胁他 你要把我烧死?!
You put me in a fire, for leverage?!
哦 我才不会烧死你 华生医生
Oh, I would never let you burn, Dr Watson.
旁边有人看着的 我可不会杀人
I had people standing by. I'm not a murderer.
不像你妻子
Unlike your wife.
我来告诉你这是怎么回事吧 华生医生
Let me explain how leverage works, Dr Watson.
圈里人都知道
For those who understand these things,
迈克罗夫特·福尔摩斯是英国最有权势的人
Mycroft Holmes is the most powerful man in the country.
好吧 除我之外
Well, apart from me.
迈克罗夫特的弱点是他侦查成瘾的弟弟夏洛克
Mycroft's pressure point is his junkie detective brother, Sherlock.
夏洛克的弱点是他最好的朋友约翰·华生
Sherlock's pressure point is his best friend, John Watson.
约翰·华生的弱点是他的妻子
John Watson's pressure point is his wife.
制住约翰·华生的妻子 就制住了迈克罗夫特
I own John Watson's wife, I own Mycroft.
他就是我得到的圣诞礼物
He's what I'm getting for Christmas.
这是交易 不是礼物
It's an exchange, not a gift.
请原谅 但是...
Forgive me, but...
似乎我已经拿到手了
I already seem to have it.
有密码保护的
It's password protected.
为了得到密码 你必须给我你手头所有
In return for the password, you will give me any material
关于玛丽·华生的资料
in your possession pertaining to the woman I know as Mary Watson.
哦 她是个坏人 害死了好多人
Oh, she's bad, that one. So many dead people.
- 你应该看看我看到的那些  - 我不用看
- You should see what I've seen.  - I don't need to see it.
也许你会喜欢的 我就很喜欢
You might enjoy it, though. I enjoy it.
那为什么不给我们看看呢?
Then why don't you show us?
阿普尔多尔? 秘密金库
Show you Appledore? The secret vaults.
这就是你想要的?
Is that what you want?
我想要的是你手里玛丽所有的把柄
I want everything you've got on Mary.
说实话 我一直是个乐观的人
You know, I honestly expected something good.
- 我想电脑里的内容对你...  - 里面有全球定位系统
- Oh, I think you'll find the contents of that laptop...  - Include a GPS locator.
现在你哥已经发现电脑被偷
By now your brother will have noticed the theft
他的安保部队会定位到这栋房子
and the security services will be converging on this house.
他们来了就会发现我手里的惊天秘密
Having arrived, they'll find top-secret information in my hands
于是就有权利搜查我的仓库
and they have every justification to search my vaults.
然后他们会发现更多证据
They will discover further information of this kind
把我抓去坐牢了
and I will be imprisoned.
而你会被赦免 回到你的小公寓
You would be exonerated and restored to your smelly little apartment
继续和疯子夫妇一起办案
to solve crimes with Mr and Mrs Psychopath.
迈克罗夫特等这一天已经等了好久了
Mycroft has been looking for this opportunity for a long time.
他会非常非常为你骄傲的
He'll be a very, very proud big brother.
就算你知道真相 也不能阻止它的发生
The fact that you know it's going to happen isn't going to stop it.
那我为什么还笑得出来? 快问我
Then why am I smiling? Ask me.
你为什么还在笑?
Why are you smiling?
因为夏洛克·福尔摩斯犯了个天大的错误
Because Sherlock Holmes has made one enormous mistake,
这个错误会害死所有他爱的人
which will destroy the lives of everyone he loves.
以及他珍惜的一切
And everything he holds dear.
请跟我去看看阿普尔多尔金库吧
Let me show you the Appledore vaults.
这就是金库入口
The entrance to my vaults.
我把东西都放在这里
This is where I keep you all.
好吧 金库在哪里?
OK, so where are the vaults, then?
地下室? 什么地下室? 这座房子里根本没有地下室
Vaults? What vaults? There are no vaults beneath this building.
这就是全部
They're all in here.
阿普尔多尔地下室是我的记忆宫殿
The Appledore vaults are my mind palace.
你知道记忆宫殿的 是吧 夏洛克?
You know about mind palaces, don't you, Sherlock?
怎样才能记住每一件事 用图像记录
How to store information so you never forget it, by picturing it.
我坐在这里 闭上眼睛 来到我的地下室
I just sit here, I close my eyes and down I go to my vaults.
我可以去地下室里的任何地方
I can go anywhere inside my vaults.
在记忆里
My memories.
我看到了华生太太的档案
I'll look at the files on Mrs Watson.
嗯
Hmm.
哦 这张是我最喜欢的
Oh, this is one of my favourites.
太动人了
Oh, it's so exciting.
为中情局做的所有勾当
All those wet jobs for the CIA.
她做自由职业了一段时间 坏姑娘
Ooh, she's gone a bit freelance now, bad girl.
哦 她可真够调皮的
Oh, she's so wicked.
我懂你为什么喜欢她了
I can really see why you like her.
现在明白了吗?
You see?
这里根本没有什么文件是吧?
So there are no documents, you don't actually have anything here?
有时候如果真的有必要
Oh, sometimes I send out for something,
我会写下点什么 但通常我只是放在记忆里
if I really need it, but mostly I just remember it all.
我不懂
I don't understand.
- 你应该把这句话印在衣服上  - 你把一切放在记忆里?
- You should have that on a T-shirt.  - You just remember it all?
认识就是一切 知道就是得到
It's all about knowledge, everything is. Knowing is owning.
如果你只是知道 就没办法证明
But if you just know it, then you don't have proof.
证明? 我为什么要证明?
Proof? What would I need proof for?
我就在传媒界 笨蛋
I'm in news, you moron.
我不需要证明 只需要让它出版
I don't have to prove it, I just have to print it.
说到新闻...
Speaking of news...
明天你们俩都会被大量报道
you'll both be heavily featured tomorrow.
报道说你们想将国家机密卖给我
Trying to sell state secrets to me.
啧啧
Tut tut.
我们出去吧 他们很快就到了
Let's go outside. They'll be here shortly.
我等不及要看你们被逮捕啦
Can't wait to see you arrested.
夏洛克 我们要怎么做?
Sherlock, do we have a plan?
夏洛克?
Sherlock?
他们不着急是吧?
They're taking their time, aren't they?
我还是不明白
I still don't understand.
这句话可以印在T恤的后面
And there's the back of the T-shirt.
你就是知道... 那有什么用呢?
You just know things... how does that work?
我就是喜欢你这副士兵嘴脸 真想打一拳
I just love your little soldier face. I'd like to punch it.
把脸伸过来一会儿
Bring it over here a minute.
伸过来 为了玛丽 把脸伸过来
Come on. For Mary. Bring me your face.
弯腰 把脸伸过来
Lean forward a bit and stick your face out.
麻烦你啦
Please.
现在 我可以弹吗?
Now, can I flick it?
看着我 可以弹吗?
Look at me. Can I flick your face?
真是爱不释手 我可以弹一整天
I just love doing this. I could do it all day.
听好了 是这样的 约翰
Well, it works like this, John.
我知道玛丽杀了哪些人 伤了哪些人
I know who Mary hurt and killed.
我知道上哪去找恨她的人
I know where to find people who hate her.
知道他们住在哪 也知道他们的电话号码
I know where they live, I know their phone numbers.
全部都在我的记忆宫殿里
All in my mind palace, all of it.
我现在就能给他们打电话 让你的日子天翻地覆
I could phone them right now and tear your whole life down
我会的
and I will,
除非你让我弹你的脸
unless you let me flick your face.
我就是这么对别人的
This is what I do to people.
也就是这么对整个国家的
This is what I do to whole countries.
就因为我有情报
Just because I know.
可以弹你的眼睛吗?
Can I do your eye now?
你可以不让眼睛闭上吗?
See if you can keep it open, hmm?
来嘛 为了玛丽 把眼睛睁开
Come on, for Mary. Keep it open.
夏洛克?
Sherlock?
让他弹吧 对不起 就... 让他弹吧
Let him. I'm sorry, just... let him.
嗯? 来嘛 把眼睛睁开
Hmm? Come on, eye open.
很难 是不是?
It's difficult, isn't it?
珍宁成功了一次 发出来的声音可好笑了
Janine managed to once. She makes the funniest noises.
夏洛克·福尔摩斯 约翰·华生 和那个男人保持距离
Sherlock Holmes and John Watson, stand away from that man.
好戏开始啦 福尔摩斯先生
Here we go, Mr Holmes.
再问一次 阿普尔多尔地下室
To clarify, Appledore's vaults only exist in your mind,
只存在于你的意识中 对吗?
nowhere else, just there?
地下室没有实体 从来如此
They're not real, they never have been.
夏洛克·福尔摩斯 约翰·华生 后退!
Sherlock Holmes and John Watson, step away!
没关系 他们动不了我
It's fine, they're harmless.
目标没有携带武器 目标没有携带武器
Target is not armed, I repeat target is not armed.
夏洛克 我们怎么办?
Sherlock, what do we do?
不怎么办 什么都不做
Nothing. There is nothing to be done.
我不是坏人 也没有什么邪恶计划
Oh, I'm not a villain, I have no evil plan.
我是个商人 只为求财 刚好你是财源之一
I'm a businessman, acquiring assets. You happen to be one of them.
对不起 这次你当不成英雄了 福尔摩斯先生
Sorry, no chance for you to be a hero this time, Mr Holmes.
夏洛克·福尔摩斯 约翰·华生 立刻远离那个男人!
Sherlock Holmes and John Watson, stand away from that man. Do it now!
你得调查清楚
Oh, do your research.
我不是什么英雄 我是个反社会狂
I'm not a hero, I'm a high-functioning sociopath.
圣诞快乐!
Merry Christmas!
目标被击毙 目标被击毙
Man down, man down.
离我远点 约翰! 站远点!
Get away from me, John! Stay well back!
天啊 夏洛克!
Christ, Sherlock!
不要开枪! 不要向夏洛克·福尔摩斯开枪!
Don't fire! Do not fire on Sherlock Holmes!
不要开枪!
Do not fire!
天啊 夏洛克!
Oh Christ, Sherlock!
替我向玛丽问声好 告诉她现在安全了
Give my love to Mary. Tell her she's safe now.
夏洛克
Oh, Sherlock.
你都做了什么?
What have you done?
这是我同事常挂在嘴边的话
As my colleague is fond of remarking,
有时 这个国家就需要一把钝器
this country sometimes needs a blunt instrument.
同理 有时也需要匕首
Equally, it sometimes needs a dagger,
一把精准 毫无悔意的手术刀
a scalpel wielded with precision and without remorse.
夏洛克·福尔摩斯总会有发挥作用的时候
There will always come a time when we need Sherlock Holmes.
你要是碍于亲情才这么说的...
If this is some expression of familial sentiment...
说什么蠢话
Don't be absurd.
对兄弟同情泛滥不是我的习惯
I am not given to outbursts of brotherly compassion.
你也知道另一个是什么下场
You know what happened to the other one.
无论如何 无论我们把夏洛克关在哪一间监狱里
In any event, there is no prison in which we could incarcerate Sherlock
肯定每天要不得安宁
without causing a riot on a daily basis.
但另一个处置方式 还需要你的首肯
The alternative, however, would require your approval.
那种方式说不上宽容 福尔摩斯先生
Hardly merciful, Mr Holmes.
遗憾的是 我的弟弟是个杀人犯 斯莫尔伍德女士
Regrettably, Lady Smallwood, my brother is a murderer.
你会替我照顾他的 是吧?
You will look after him for me, won't you?
嗯 别担心 我会让他没好日子过的
Hmm. Don't worry. I'll keep him in trouble.
真好
That's my girl.
我以后大概都没有和约翰·华生说话的机会了
Since this is likely to be the last conversation I'll have with John Watson,
可以让我们单独聊几句吗?
would you mind if we took a moment?
来说几句吧
So here we are.
威廉·夏洛克·斯科特·福尔摩斯
William Sherlock Scott Holmes.
什么?
Sorry?
这是我的全名 如果你要给孩子取名 可以参考
That's the whole of it. If you're looking for baby names.
不用了 我们做了B超 可以确定是个女孩
No, we've had a scan, we're pretty sure it's a girl.
好吧
Oh. OK.
是啊
Yeah.
要知道实际上 我不知道要说什么
You know, actually, I can't think of a single thing to say.
我也不知道
No, neither can I.
游戏结束了
The game is over.
永远不会结束的 约翰
The game is never over, John.
但会有新的玩家加入
But there may be some new players now.
- 没事 到最后东风神会做个了断  - 什么意思?
- That's OK, the East Wind takes us all in the end.  - What's that?
小时候我哥哥跟我说的一个故事
It's a story my brother told me when we were kids.
东风神摧枯拉朽 有万钧之力 席卷万物
The East Wind is a terrifying force that lays waste to all in its path.
它找出那些无用的东西 将它们连根拔起
It seeks out the unworthy and plucks them from the earth.
那就是在说我啦
That was generally me.
- 听着不错!  - 我哥哥就是废话多
- Nice!  - He's a rubbish big brother.
那你现在要怎么办? 你要去哪里?
So what about you, then? Where are you actually going now?
去东欧执行什么卧底任务
Oh, some undercover work in Eastern Europe.
去多久?
For how long?
据我哥哥估计得六个月 他没说错过
Six months, my brother estimates. He's never wrong.
那之后呢?
And then what?
谁知道呢?
Who knows?
约翰 有些事我得告诉你 我一直都想说
John, there's something I should say, I've meant to say always
但是从来没说出口
and I never have.
既然我们以后大概都见不着了 我就现在说了吧
Since it's unlikely we'll ever meet again, I might as well say it now.
夏洛克是女孩子的名字
Sherlock is actually a girl's name.
才怪
It's not.
搞不好你就信了嘛
It was worth a try.
我们不会给女儿起和你一样的名字
We're not naming our daughter after you.
跟我同名也不错啊
Oh, I think it could work.
为了我们在一起的好时光 约翰
To the very best of times, John.
史密斯把球带入禁区 很有希望进球
Smith brings it inside. This looks good.
卡桑德拉接球射门 没射中!
Cassandra comes in for a shot. Ooh, he missed it!
嘿 电视有点问题 兄弟 电视坏了
Oi, there's something wrong with the telly. There's something wrong with the telly, mate.
那是谁?
Who's that?
想我吗?
Did you miss me?
你想我吗? 你想我吗?
Did you miss me? Did you miss me?
怎么可能?
How is this possible?
不知道 但全国的电视上都看得到
We don't know, but it's on every screen in the country.
同时在所有频道上播出
Every screen simultaneously.
首相知道了吗?
Has the Prime Minister been told?
迈克罗夫特呢?
And Mycroft?
但这不可能 怎么可能呢
But that's not possible. That is simply not possible.
- 出什么事了?  - 先生? 您哥哥的电话
- What's happened?  - Sir? It's your brother.
迈克罗夫特?
Mycroft?
你好呀 小弟弟 放逐之行如何了?
Hello, little brother. How's the exile going?
飞机才起飞4分钟
I've only been gone four minutes.
我希望你已经学乖了
Well, I certainly hope you've learnt your lesson.
现在情况是 我们需要你
As it turns out, you're needed.
天啊 别想一出是一出!
Oh, for God's sake, make up your mind!
这次是谁需要我?
Who needs me this time?
你想我了吗?
Did you miss me?
全英国
England.
但他已经死呀 你不是告诉我莫里亚蒂已经死了呀?
But he's dead. I mean, you told me he was dead, Moriarty?
死透了 他自己往脑袋开了一枪
Absolutely. Blew his own brains out.
那他怎么又回来了?
So how can he be back?
如果他真复活了 最好穿暖和点
Well if he is, he'd better wrap up warm.
东风神就要来了
There's an East Wind coming.